Register of the Sidney Hook papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Audiovisual File, 1953-1988 (Boxes 184-185, Record cabinet, Photo file)
  - Sound tape reels and sound cassettes
    - Jefferson Lecture Series by Sidney Hook, University of California, Berkeley, 1961 March 9-16; 2.0 sound tape reels (Box 184, Tape 12-13)
      Part 2: Title: Democracy and Judicial Review, Jefferson Lecture: The Paradoxes of Freedom #2 Speaker: Sidney Hook Remarks: About 15' of end of lecture not recorded. Recorded at: U. C. Berkeley Date: Mar. 14, 1961
      Beginning by recalling that Jefferson identified himself as a democrat in an era of suspicion of democracy, Hook examines the intersection, perhaps antagonism, of judicial review and democracy. He then looks at various Founding Fathers' views on the topic, including Jefferson's dislike of judicial review.
      Part 3: Title: Intelligence, Conscience and Revolution Speaker: Sidney Hook Remarks: Jefferson Lecture: The Paradoxes of Freedom #3 Recorded at: U.C. Berkeley Date: Mar. 16, 1961
    - "Freedom, Peace, and Prospects for Survival," speech, Monterey Peninsula College, 1961 December 14; 2.0 sound tape reels (Box 184, Tape 14-15)
      Use copy reference number: 90003_a_0009058
      Sidney Hook delivered this lecture at Monterey Peninsula College. He speaks about the threat of communism to freedom, both in the United States and abroad.
    - "The Symbols, Myths and Rationale of Revolution," speech, Central Washington State College, 1967 April 19; 1.0 sound tape reel (Box 185, Tape 16)
      Use copy reference number: 90003_a_0009059
      6th Annual Symposium Speaker: Dr. Sidney Hook Topic: "The Symbols, Myths and Rationale of Revolution" April 19, 1967 CWSC Campus
      Originally recorded by: Audiovisual Department Central Wash. State College
    - Speech by Joseph Katz, "Why Students Revolt,", 1969 October 14; 1.0 sound tape reel (Box 185, Tape 17)
      Use copy reference number: 90003_a_0009061
    - 80th birthday tribute, 1982 October 29; 1.0 sound cassette (Box 185, Cassette 18)
      Use copy reference number: 90003_a_0009045
    - "Speaking of Everything," radio interview with Howard Cosell, 1987 June 14; 1.0 sound cassette (Box 185, Cassette 27)
      Use copy reference number: 90003_a_0009049
    - Oral history interview with Norman Podhoretz, 1988 October 25; 1.0 sound cassettes (Box 185, Cassette 28-29)
      Use copy reference number: 90003_a_0009050
    - New York University memorial service for Sidney Hook, 1989 September 29; 2.0 sound cassettes (Box 185, Cassette 30-31)
      Use copy reference number: 90003_a_0009053
      A series of speakers at New York University remember and eulogize Sidney Hook.
    - Sidney Hook interviewed by Daniel Rice, 1986 June 17; 1.0 sound cassette (Box 185)
      Use copy reference number: 90003_a_0009063
      From the accessioned cassette sleeve: In researching for my book Reinhold Niebuhr and John Dewey: An American Odyssey (Albany, SUNY Press, 1973) Sidney Hook granted me this interview. On June 17, 1986. The first few seconds were not recorded. Follow-up questions of mine were answered by mail. Copies of my letter of August 14, 1986 and Professor Hook's August 27, 1986 reply are enclosed.
  - Sound disc. "Si J'avais une Faucille," produced by the Internationale de la Risistance, France, 1983 (Record cabinet)
  - Videocassettes
    - "Visions of the Social Order,", 1986 (Box 185, Folder 32-33)
    - "On Being a Jew," television interview, circa 1987-1988 (Folder 34)
    - "Hook Evaluates Liberalism," Firing Line, 1987 July 24 (Folder 35)
    - U. S. Senate testimony by Leo Cherne, Alexandra Costa and others relating to Afghanistan, 1987 October 9 (Folder 36)
    - Interview, television broadcast in Taiwan?, circa 1988 (Folder 37)
    - Speech by S. I. Hayakawa relating to the organization U. S. English, 1988 (Folder 38)
  - Photographs, 1930-1987 (Photo file)
    19 prints, 6 contact sheets, 15 postcards / 2 envelopes.
    - 6 contact sheets and 17 prints of Sidney Hook and others, circa 1930s-1987; 1 print of Herbert Solow, John MacDonald, Jean van Heijenoort and others in Mexico, 1938; 15 postcards (7 duplicates) of scenes of Korea and Lebanon, undated (Envelope A)
    - 1 print of Sidney Hook by Alfred Eisenstaedt, 1956 (Envelope mB)
- Addendum File, 1922-2002 (Boxes 186-191)
  Addendum materials organized in 2007. Includes additional biographical information, correspondence, speeches and writings, lecture notes, subject files, audiovisual files, and oversize materials.
  - Oversize File, 1942, undated
    - Speeches and writings. "The Philosophy of American Pragmatism,", undated (Box 186, Folder 1)
      Printed copies of Russian and Polish translations, published in U.S. Information Agency journals Amerika (Russian) and Ameryka (Polish),
    - Photographs. Oversize photographs of Sidney Hook, 1942, undated (Box 186, Folder 2)
  - Biographical File, 1946-2002
    - Clippings and printed articles, 1964-1988
      - Clippings, 1964-1969 (Box 187, Folder 1)
      - Printed article. Edward S. Shapiro, "The Sidney Hook-Corliss Lamont Letters," Continuity, Fall 1988 (Box 187, Folder 2)
    - Communist opinion. Herbert Aptheker, "Communism and Truth: A Reply to Sidney Hook," Masses and Mainstream, 1952 (Box 187, Folder 3)
      Printed copy
    - Family. Genealogical data and school reports, 1946-1969 (Box 187, Folder 4)
    - Post-mortem commentary. New York University centennial conference on Sidney Hook and His Legacy in the Twentieth Century proceedings, obituary, and letters exchanged between Ernest B. Hook and John P. Diggins, 1989-2002 (Box 187, Folder 5)
    - Stroke, 1980 (Box 187, Folder 6)
      Messages written in the hospital
  - Correspondence, 1922-1989
    - General, 1941-1989 (Box 187, Folder 7)
    - Boorstin, Daniel, 1970 (Box 187, Folder 8)
    - Buck, R. Creighton, 1971 (Box 187, Folder 9)
    - Budenz, Louis Francis, 1967 (Box 187, Folder 10)
    - Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1964-1968 (Box 187, Folder 11)
    - Continuum (Justus George Lawler), 1963 (Box 187, Folder 12)
    - Decter, Midge, undated (Box 187, Folder 13)
    - Decter, Moshe, 1956-1967 (Box 187, Folder 14)
    - Drachkovitch, Milorad M., 1968 (Box 187, Folder 15)
    - Gale, Richard M., 1967 (Box 187, Folder 16)
    - Grunbaum, Adolf, 1984 (Box 187, Folder 17)
    - Hester, James M., 1968 (Box 187, Folder 18)
    - Hook, Ann, 1930-1958 (Box 187, Folder 19-23)
    - Hook, Carrie, 1922-1949 (Box 188, Folder 1-4)
    - Hook, John, 1941-1966 (Box 188, Folder 5)
    - Hook, Susan, 1961 (Box 188, Folder 6)
    - Jukes, Thomas H., 1966 (Box 188, Folder 7)
    - Kline, George L., 1965 (Box 188, Folder 8)
    - Knopfelmacher, Frank, 1967 (Box 188, Folder 9)
    - Konvitz, Milton R., 1965 (Box 188, Folder 10)
    - Kristol, Irving, 1968 (Box 188, Folder 11)
    - Kurtz, Paul, 1968 (Box 188, Folder 12)
    - Labedz, Leopold, 1968 (Box 188, Folder 13)
    - Lamont, Corliss, 1968 (Box 188, Folder 14)
    - Lerner, Michael, 1966 (Box 188, Folder 15)
    - Maitre, Joachim, 1979 (Box 188, Folder 16)
    - Mendelowitz, Jeanette, 1925-1926 (Box 188, Folder 17)
    - New York Times, 1953-1971 (Box 188, Folder 18)
    - Nielson, Kai, 1967 (Box 188, Folder 19)
    - Nomad, Max, 1966 (Box 188, Folder 20)
    - Polisuk, Celia, 1923-1925 (Box 188, Folder 21)
    - Pomerance, Is, 1924 (Box 188, Folder 22)
    - Ross, Ralph G., 1968 (Box 188, Folder 23)
    - Schaffer, Mary, 1924-1926 (Box 188, Folder 24)
    - Schwartz, Beulah, 1924-1925 (Box 188, Folder 25)
    - Shepard, John D., 1968 (Box 188, Folder 26)
    - Silone, Ignazio, 1951 (Box 188, Folder 27)
    - Silvers, Robert, 1969 (Box 188, Folder 28)
    - Solow, Herbert, undated (Box 188, Folder 29)
    - Trilling, Lionel, undated (Box 188, Folder 30)
    - Wald, Alan, 1974-1984 (Box 188, Folder 31)
    - Walter, Edward, 1968 (Box 188, Folder 32)
    - Westbrook, Robert, 1987 (Box 188, Folder 33)
    - Wolfe, Ella, 1968 (Box 188, Folder 34)
    - Unidentified (Leonore, last name unknown), 1925-1927 (Box 188, Folder 35-36)
  - Speeches and Writings, 1925-1988
    - "The Fifth Amendment: A Problem in Law and Morals,", undated. (Box 190, Folder 1)
      Speech. Typescript
    - Letter to the editor, New York Times, undated. (Box 190, Folder 2)
      Relates to the Fifth Amendment. Typescript
    - "New York as an Educational Center,", undated. (Box 190, Folder 3)
      Typescript
    - Notes on philosophy, 1925-1926. (Box 190, Folder 4)
      Holograph notebook
    - Towards the Understanding of Karl Marx, 1933
      - Book jackets (Box 190, Folder 5)
      - Printed copy annotated by Leon Trotsky (Box 190, Folder 5)
      - Original (Other Safe)
      - Photocopy, with transcription and translation of annotations (Box 190, Folder 6)
    - "A Systematic Philosophy, and Testament, by Mr. Russell," New York Times, Jan. 2, 1949. (Box 190, Folder 7)
      Review of Bertrand Russell, Human Knowledge: Its Scope and Limits. Holograph
    - "Bread, Freedom and Businessmen," Fortune, Sept. 1951. (Box 190, Folder 8)
      Printed copy of German translation, published in Monat, undated
    - "Red Teachers Can't Claim Objectivity," Square Bulletin [Washington Square College, New York University], Dec. 17, 1952. (Box 190, Folder 9)
      Reply to Herbert Aptheker's comments on Hook's article "Communists Practice 'Educational Fraud.'" Printed copy, and printed copy of Aptheker's comments, 1952
    - "Some Observations on the 'Report of the Special Committee on Faculty Responsibility toward Governmental Investigative Agencies' [of Washington Square College, New York University],", April 17, 1953. (Box 190, Folder 10)
    - Humanities Curriculum Seminar, Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, Chicago, May 14-16, 1953. (Box 190, Folder 11)
      (seminar director). Workbook and notes
    - Letter to the editor, New York Times, 5/20/1957. (Box 190, Folder 12)
      (date written) Relates to comments on Hook's book Common Sense and the Fifth Amendment. Typescript
    - "Prof. Hook and the Fifth Amendment," Frontier, Aug. 1957. (Box 190, Folder 13)
      Letter to the editor relating to a review by John Caughey of Common Sense and the Fifth Amendment. Printed copy, and printed copy of Caughey's response, 1957
    - The Paradoxes of Freedom, 1962 (Box 190, Folder 14)
      Galleys of review by Arnold S. Kaufman, undated
    - Moral and Ethical Considerations in the Use of Mass Casualty Weapons, panel discussion, Washington, D.C., April 9, 1965. (Box 190, Folder 15)
      (panel member) Transcript of discussion
    - Letter to the editor, New York Times, Aug. 1965. (Box 190, Folder 16)
      (date written). Reply to letter to the editor by Haakon Chevalier regarding Hook's review of his book Oppenheimer. Typescript, typescript of Chevalier's letter, correspondence, and clipping, 1965
    - Contemporary Philosophy, 1968 (Box 190, Folder 17)
      Pamphlet. Holograph (incomplete), typescript (incomplete), outline, contract, and correspondence, 1965
    - Letter to the editor, Playboy, Aug. 5, 1968. (Box 190, Folder 18)
      (date written) Relates to Playboy interview with William Sloane Coffin. Typescript, printed copy of Coffin interview, and correspondence, 1968
    - In Defense of Academic Freedom, 1971 (Box 190, Folder 19)
      (editor). Letter, 1970
    - "Lenin and the Communist International," Russian Review, Jan. 1973. (Box 190, Folder 20)
      Review of Branko Lazitch and Milorad M. Drachkovitch, Lenin and the Comintern, Vol. I. Holograph
    - "John Reed, the Romantic," New Republic, Sept. 29, 1973. (Box 190, Folder 21)
      Review of Barbara Gelb, So Short a Time. Holograph
    - Oral history interviews with Ernest B. Hook, Dec. 1983. (Box 189, Folder 1-8)
      Transcripts
    - "The Event-Making Man," The World and I, Feb. 1988. (Box 190, Folder 22)
      Letter and contract, 1987
  - Lecture Notes, undated
    - General (Box 190, Folder 23)
    - Augustine (Box 190, Folder 24)
    - Berkeley (Box 190, Folder 25)
    - Descartes (Box 190, Folder 26)
    - Fifth Amendment (Box 190, Folder 27)
    - Hume (Box 190, Folder 28)
    - Leibnitz (Box 190, Folder 29)
    - Locke (Box 190, Folder 30)
    - Logic (Box 190, Folder 31)
    - Spinoza (Box 190, Folder 32)
    - Whitehead (Box 190, Folder 33)
  - Subject File, 1929-1986
    - General. Printed miscellany, 1933-1986 (Box 191, Folder 1)
    - Communism. Pamphlets, 1929-1951. (Box 191, Folder 2)
      Includes On the Road to Bolshevization; Albert Verblin, The Struggle for Power; and anti-communist French pamphlets
    - Einstein, Albert. Printed article, 1949 (Box 191, Folder 3)
    - Political crimes and offenses-Soviet Union. Pamphlet. Friedrich Adler et al., The Moscow Trial and the Labour and Socialist International, 1931 (Box 191, Folder 4)
    - United States. Constitution, Relates to the Fifth Amendment and legal status of American Communists. Speeches, clippings, printed articles, Congressional hearing transcripts, and judicial decisions, 1953-1960 (Box 191, Folder 5-6)
    - World War, 1939-1945. Pamphlet. War Aims, Peace Terms, and the World after the War, 1941 (Box 191, Folder 7)
  - Audiovisual File, 1929-1984
    - Sound cassette, 1984 August 4 (Box 191, Folder 8)
      Recording of discussion between Sidney Hook and Theodore Draper.
    - Caricatures depicting Sidney Hook, undated (Box 191, Folder 9)
    - Photographs depicting Sidney Hook, circa 1929-1948 (Box 191, Folder 10)
      and drawing of Dewey Commission hearings, 1937
- Incremental Materials (Boxes 192-199)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described. Contact us at hooverarchivesinfo@stanford.edu